Worldwide, over 1.5 billion people experience armed conflict.
يعاني أكثر من 1.5 مليار شخص حول العالم من صراع مسلح.
In response, people are forced to flee their country,
ونتيجة لذلك، يُجبر الناس على الهرب من بلادهم،
leaving over 15 million refugees.
مما يخلف أكثر من 15 مليون لاجئ.
Children, without a doubt,
إن الأطفال من دون شك،
are the most innocent and vulnerable victims ...
هم أكثر الضحايا براءة و استضعافاً...
but not just from the obvious physical dangers,
لكن ليس فقط بسبب الأخطار الجسدية الظاهرة،
but from the often unspoken effects that wars have on their families.
بل بسبب التأثيرات المخفية التي خلفتها الحروب على عائلاتهم.
The experiences of war leave children at a real high risk
تركت تجارب الحرب الأطفال في مستوى عالٍ
for the development of emotional and behavioral problems.
من خطر تطور المشاكل العاطفية والسلوكية.
Children, as we can only imagine,
الأطفال، كما يمكننا أن نتخيل،
will feel worried, threatened and at risk.
سيشعرون بالقلق، والتهديد و بالخطر.
But there is good news.
لكن هناك بارقة أمل.
The quality of care that children receive in their families
إن جودة الرعاية التي يتلقاها الأطفال في عائلاتهم
can have a more significant effect on their well-being
يمكن أن يكون لها تأثير كبير على عافيتهم
than from the actual experiences of war that they have been exposed to.
أكثر من التجارب الفعلية للحرب التي قد تعرضوا لها.
So actually, children can be protected
لذا بالفعل يمكن حماية الأطفال
by warm, secure parenting during and after conflict.
من خلال التربية الوالدية الدافئة والآمنة خلال وبعد النزاع.
In 2011, I was a first-year PhD student
لقد كنت طالبة دكتوراة في سنتي الأولى في عام 2001
in the University of Manchester School of Psychological Sciences.
في جامعة مانشستر، قسم العلوم النفسية.
Like many of you here,
ومثل الكثير منكم هنا،
I watched the crisis in Syria unfold in front of me on the TV.
شاهدت الأزمة السورية تتكشف أمامي على التلفاز.
My family is originally from Syria,
إن أصول عائلتي سورية،
and very early on,
وفي وقت سابق،
I lost several family members in really horrifying ways.
فقدت العديد من من أفراد عائلتي بطرق مروعة.
I'd sit and I'd gather with my family and watch the TV.
وكنت أجلس واجتمع مع عائلتي نشاهد التلفاز.
We've all seen those scenes:
رأينا كلنا هذه المشاهد :
bombs destroying buildings,
من قنابل تدمر المباني،
chaos, destruction
فوضى عارمة، و دمار في كل مكان
and people screaming and running.
وأناس يركضون ويصرخون.
It was always the people screaming and running that really got me the most,
ولطالما كان صراخ الناس وفرارهم أكثر ما أثر بي،
especially those terrified-looking children.
وبالأخص منظر الأطفال المرعوبين.
I was a mother to two young, typically inquisitive children.
كنت أماً لطفلين فضوليين بعادتهم.
They were five and six then,
كانوا بعمر الخامسة والسادسة آنذاك،
at an age where they typically asked lots and lots of questions,
وفي عُمرٍ يكون من المعتاد أن يسألوا فيه الكثير من الاسئلة،
and expected real, convincing answers.
ويتوقعون الحصول على أجوبة حقيقية ومقنعة للغاية.
So, I began to wonder what it might be like
لذا بدأت أتسائل، كيف كان سيبدو الأمر
to parent my children in a war zone and a refugee camp.
أن أربي أطفالي في منطقة حرب وفي مخيم لاجئين.
Would my children change?
هل سيتغير أطفالي ؟
Would my daughter's bright, happy eyes lose their shine?
هل ستفقد عيون ابنتي المشرقة و السعيدة لمعانها ؟
Would my son's really relaxed and carefree nature become fearful and withdrawn?
هل ستصبح طبيعة ابني المرتاحة والسعيدة، خائفة ومنطوية ؟
How would I cope?
كيف يمكن أن أتأقلم ؟
Would I change?
هل سأتغير؟
As psychologists and parent trainers,
وكأخصائيين نفسين ومدربين للآباء،
we know that arming parents with skills in caring for their children
نعلم أن الآباء المتسلحين بمهارات العناية بالأطفال
can have a huge effect on their well-being,
يمكن أن يكون لهم تأثيرٌ بالغٌ على صحتهم،
and we call this parent training.
ونطلق على هذا الأمر تدريب الآباء.
The question I had was,
والسؤال الذي راودني،
could parent training programs be useful for families
هل سيكون برنامج تدريب الآباء مفيداً للعائلات
while they were still in war zones or refugee camps?
طيلة تواجدهم في مناطق الحرب أو في مخيمات اللاجئين؟
Could we reach them with advice or training
هل من الممكن أن نمدهم بالنصح والتدريب
that would help them through these struggles?
الذي سيساعدهم على تخطي هذه الصعوبات ؟
So I approached my PhD supervisor,
لذا اقترحت على مشرفي في رسالة الدكتوراة،
Professor Rachel Calam,
البروفيسور (رايشل كالم)،
with the idea of using my academic skills to make some change in the real world.
فكرة استخدام مهارتي الأكاديمية لإحداث تغيير في العالم الحقيقي.
I wasn't quite sure what exactly I wanted to do.
لم أكن متأكدة ماذا أريد أن أفعل بالتحديد.
She listened carefully and patiently,
لقد استمعت إلي باهتمام وصبر،
and then to my joy she said,
ومن ثم أبهجتني بقولها،
"If that's what you want to do, and it means so much to you,
" إذا كان هذا الأمر يعني لك كثيراً وتريدين فعله،
then let's do it.
إذاً لنفعله.
Let's find ways to see if parent programs
لنجد طريقة ما، نرى من خلالها إذا كانت برامج التربية الوالدية
can be useful for families in these contexts."
مجدية للعائلات في هذه الظروف."
So for the past five years, myself and my colleagues --
لذا كنت أنا وزملائي على مدى الخمس سنين الماضية
Prof. Calam and Dr. Kim Cartwright --
البروفيسور كالم والدكتور كيم كارترايت --
have been working on ways to support families
نعمل على إيجاد طرق تدعم العائلات
that have experienced war and displacement.
التي عاشت مقاسي الحرب والنزوح.
Now, to know how to help families that have been through conflict
والآن لمعرفة كيف من الممكن مساعدة العائلات التى مرت بنزاع مسلح
support their children,
لدعم أطفالهم،
the first step must obviously be to ask them what they're struggling with,
من البديهي أن تكون أول خطوة هي السؤال عن الأمور التي يعانون منها،
right?
صحيح؟
I mean, it seems obvious.
أعني، يبدو أنه أمر واضح.
But it's often those that are the most vulnerable,
ولكن في كثير من الأحيان يكون الأشخاص المستضعفون،
that we're trying to support,
الذين نحاول أن ندعمهم،
that we actually don't ask.
هم بالذات الذين لا نقوم بسؤالهم.
How many times have we just assumed we know exactly the right thing
كم مرة افترضنا أننا نقوم بالشيء الصحيح تماما
that's going to help someone or something without actually asking them first?
الذي سيساعد شخصا ما دون أن نسألهم أولا؟
So I travelled to refugee camps in Syria and in Turkey,
لذا سافرت إلى مخيمات اللاجئين في سوريا وتركيا.
and I sat with families, and I listened.
و جلست مع العائلات وأصغيت لهم.
I listened to their parenting challenges,
أصغيت إلى تحديات التربية الوالدية التي تواجههم،
I listened to their parenting struggles
وأصغيت إلى صعوبات التربية الوالدية لديهم
and I listened to their call for help.
ومن ثم أصغيت لنداء استغاثتهم.
And sometimes that was just paused,
وفي بعض الأحيان كان كل ذلك الأمر يتوقف،
as all I could do was hold hands with them
وكل ما أستطيع فعله أن أمسك أياديهم
and just join them in silent crying and prayer.
ومشاركتهم بصمت في البكاء والدعاء.
They told me about their struggles,
حدثوني عن معاناتهم،
they told me about the rough, harsh refugee camp conditions
وأيضاً أخبروني عن ظروف المخيم القاسية والصعبة
that made it hard to focus on anything but practical chores
التي حالت بينهم وبين التركيز على أي شيء سوى الأعمال الأساسية
like collecting clean water.
كالبحث عن الماء النظيف.
They told me how they watched their children withdraw;
وأخبروني أيضاً كيف شاهدوا انْطواء أطفالهم،
the sadness, depression, anger,
والحزن والاكتئاب والغضب،
bed-wetting, thumb-sucking, fear of loud noises,
تبليل الفراش ومص الإبهام والخوف من الأصوات العالية،
fear of nightmares --
والخوف من الكوابيس --
terrifying, terrifying nightmares.
الكوابيس المرعبة للغاية.
These families had been through what we had been watching on the TV.
لقد مرت هذا العائلات بكل ما شاهدناه على التلفاز.
The mothers --
الأمهات --
almost half of them were now widows of war,
ما يقارب من نصف عددهن، كن أرامل بسبب الحرب،
or didn't even know if their husbands were dead or alive --
أو حتى لم يعرفن ما إذا كان أزواجهن أمواتا أو أحياءً --
described how they felt they were coping so badly.
وهن يصفن شعورهن، كن يتأقلمن مع الأمر بشكل سيء للغاية.
They watched their children change and they had no idea how to help them.
لقد شاهدن تغير أطفالهن ولم يكن يملكن أدنى فكرة عن كيفية مساعدتهم.
They didn't know how to answer their children's questions.
ولم يكن يعرفن كيف يجبن على أسئلة أطفالهن.
What I found incredibly astonishing and so motivational
ولقد كنت مندهشة ومتحمسةً بما وجدت
was that these families were so motivated to support their children.
من دوافع لدى هذه العائلات لدعم أطفالهم.
Despite all these challenges they faced,
رغم كل التحديات التي واجهوها،
they were trying to help their children.
كانوا يحاولون مساعدة أطفالهم.
They were making attempts at seeking support from NGO workers,
وكانوا يحاولون طلب المساعدة من عاملي المنظمات غير الحكومية،
from refugee camp teachers,
ومن معلمي مخيم اللاجئين،
professional medics,
ومن الأطباء،
other parents.
ومن آباء آخرين.
One mother I met had only been in a camp for four days,
قابلت أماً كانت في المخيم منذ أربعة أيام فقط،
and had already made two attempts
وسبق أن حاولت مرتين
at seeking support for her eight-year-old daughter
لطلب المساعدة من أجل ابنتها ذات الثمانية أعوام
who was having terrifying nightmares.
التي كانت تعاني من كوابيس مرعبة.
But sadly, these attempts are almost always useless.
ولكن لسوء الحظ، باءت كل هذه المحاولات بالفشل.
Refugee camp doctors, when available,
وغالبا ما يكون أطباء المخيم في حال تواجدهم،
are almost always too busy,
مشغولين جداُ،
or don't have the knowledge or the time for basic parenting supports.
أو لا يملكون الوقت والمعرفة بأساسيات دعم التربية الوالدية.
Refugee camp teachers and other parents are just like them --
وكما هو الحال أيضاً عند معلمي المخيم والآباء الآخرين --
part of a new refugee community who's struggling with new needs.
فهم جزء من مجتمع مخيم لاجئين جديد يعاني من احتياجات جديدة.
So then we began to think.
لذا بدأنا بالتفكير.
How could we help these families?
كيف يمكننا مساعدة هذه العائلات ؟
The families were struggling with things much bigger than they could cope with.
إن العائلات تعاني من أمور أكبر من أن تستطيع التعامل معها.
The Syrian crisis made it clear
حيث وضحت الأزمة السورية هذا الأمر
how incredibly impossible it would be to reach families on an individual level.
أنه كيف من الصعب الوصول للعائلات على المستوى الفردي.
How else could we help them?
إذاً كيف يمكننا أن نساعدعم بطريقة أخرى ؟
How would we reach families at a population level
كيف من الممكن الوصول إلى العائلات على المستوى السكاني
and low costs
وبأقل التكاليف
in these terrifying, terrifying times?
وفي هذه الأوقات المرعبة ؟
After hours of speaking to NGO workers,
وبعد ساعات من الحديث مع عاملي المنظمة غير الحكومية،
one suggested a fantastic innovative idea
أقترح أحد العمال فكرة رائعة
of distributing parenting information leaflets via bread wrappers --
تقوم على توزيع منشورات تحتوي على معلومات للتربية الوالدية من خلال مغلفات الخبز --
by humanitarian workers.
من قبل عاملي المساعدات الإنسانية.
So that's what we did.
وكان هذا ما قمنا بفعله.
The bread wrappers haven't changed at all in their appearance,
لم يتغير شكل مغلفات الخبز على الإطلاق،
except for the addition of two pieces of paper.
إنما تم إضافة ورقتين فحسب.
One was a parenting information leaflet that had basic advice and information
إحداهما كانت نشرة معلومات تحتوي على نصائح و معلومات أساسية
that normalized to the parent what they might be experiencing,
مبسطة للوالدين عن ما يمكن أن يواجهم،
and what their child might be experiencing.
وعن ما يمكن أن يعاني منه طفلهم.
And information on how they could support themselves and their children,
بالإضافة إلي معلومات عن كيفية دعم أنفسهم وأولادهم،
such as information like spending time talking to your child,
مثل معلومات عن قضاء الوقت بالتحدث إلى أطفالك،
showing them more affection,
وإظهار المزيد من الحنان لهم،
being more patient with your child,
وأن يكونوت صبورين أكثر مع أطفالهم،
talking to your children.
والتحدث إلى أطفالك.
The other piece of paper was a feedback questionnaire,
والورقة الثانية عبارة عن استبيان تقييم،
and of course, there was a pen.
وطبعاً، هنالك قلم مع الاستبيان !
So is this simply leaflet distribution,
إذن، فهل كان الأمر مجرد توزيع منشورات،
or is this actually a possible means of delivering psychological first aid
أم هو بالفعل إحدى الطرق الممكنة لتوصيل إسعافات نفسية أولية
that provides warm, secure, loving parenting?
التي تزودهم بطرق التربية الوالدية الآمنة والدافئة والمليئة بالحب؟
We managed to distribute 3,000 of these in just one week.
تمكنا من توزيع 3.000 منشور خلال أسبوع واحد فقط.
What was incredible was we had a 60 percent response rate.
والأمر المدهش أنه تلقينا استجابة بنسبة 60%.
60 percent of the 3,000 families responded.
استجابت 60% من 3,000عائلة.
I don't know how many researchers we have here today,
لا أعلم كم باحث معنا هنا اليوم،
but that kind of response rate is fantastic.
لكن هذه نسبةٌ رائعةٌ من الاستجابة.
To have that in Manchester would be a huge achievement,
الحصول على نتيجة كهذه في جامعة (مانشستر) سيكون إنجازاً عظيماً،
let alone in a conflict zone in Syria --
ناهيك عن وجود نزاع في سوريا
really highlighting how important these kinds of messages were to families.
وقد سلط هذا الأمر الضوء على أهمية هذا النوع من الرسائل للعائلات.
I remember how excited and eager we were for the return of the questionnaires.
وأتذكر كيف كنا متلهفين ومتحمسين لرجوع الاستبيانات.
The families had left hundreds of messages --
تركت العائلات المئات من الرسائل
most incredibly positive and encouraging.
أغلبها إيجابي ومشجع.
But my favorite has got to be,
ولكن رسالتي المفضلة هي،
"Thank you for not forgetting about us and our children."
"نشكر لكم عدم نسياننا وأطفالنا."
This really illustrates the potential means
هذا الأمر حتماً سيوضح المعنى الأساسي
of the delivery of psychological first aid to families,
لعملية توصيل الإسعافات النفسية الأولية للعائلات.
and the return of feedback, too.
وأيضاً عودة التقييم.
Just imagine replicating this using other means
تخيلوا فقط استبدال هذا الأمر بوسائل أخرى
such as baby milk distribution, or female hygiene kits,
كتوزيع حليب للأطفال، أو لوازم صحية للنساء،
or even food baskets.
أو حتى بسلال طعام.
But let's bring this closer to home,
لكن لنجعل هذا الأمر أقرب لمنازلنا،
because the refugee crisis
لأن أزمة اللاجئين
is one that is having an effect on every single one of us.
لها تأثيرعلى كل واحد فينا.
We're bombarded with images daily of statistics and of photos,
نحن نُمطر يومياً بوابل من صور وإحصاءات،
and that's not surprising,
وهذا الأمر ليس مفاجئا،
because by last month,
لأنه خلال الشهر الماضي،
over one million refugees had reached Europe.
وصل أكثر من مليون لاجئ إلى أوروبا.
One million.
مليون لاجئ !
Refugees are joining our communities,
ينضم اللاجئون الآن لمجتمعاتنا،
they're becoming our neighbors,
ويصبحون جيراننا،
their children are attending our children's schools.
ويرتاد أطفالهم مدارس أطفالنا.
So we've adapted the leaflet to meet the needs of European refugees,
لذلك عدلنا النشرة لتلائم احتياجات اللاجئين الأوروبيين،
and we have them online, open-access,
هي متاحة الآن عبر الأنترنت للجميع،
in areas with a really high refugee influx.
وفي مناطق ذات تدفق عالٍ لللاجئين.
For example, the Swedish healthcare uploaded it onto their website,
مثلا، قامت منظمة الرعاية الصحية السويدية برفع النشرة على موقعها،
and within the first 45 minutes,
وبغضون أول 45 دقيقة،
it was downloaded 343 times --
تم تحمليها 343 مرة --
really highlighting how important it is
وهذا ما سلط الضوء على أهميتها
for volunteers, practitioners and other parents
للمتطوعين وللأطباء الممارسين وللآباء الآخرين
to have open-access, psychological first-aid messages.
وجلعها في متناول الجميع كإسعافات نفسية أولية.
In 2013, I was sitting on the cold, hard floor of a refugee camp tent
كنت جالسةً في عامِ 2013 في البردِ على أرضٍ قاسيةٍ لخيمةٍ في مخيمِ اللاجئين
with mothers sitting around me as I was conducting a focus group.
مع أمهات يجلسن حولي عندما كنت أرشدهم كمجموعة مركزة.
Across from me stood an elderly lady
وكانت تجلس أمامي سيدة كبيرة في سن
with what seemed to be a 13-year-old girl lying beside her,
مع فتاة يبدو أن عمرها 13 عاماً كانت مستلقية إلى جانبها،
with her head on the elderly lady's knees.
واضعة رأسها على ركبتي السيدة.
The girl stayed quiet throughout the focus group,
وكان الهدوء يهيمن على الفتاة خلال المجموعة المركزة،
not talking at all,
لم تتكلم على الإطلاق،
with her knees curled up against her chest.
وكانت تطوي ركبتيها عند صدرها.
Towards the end of the focus group,
على مشارف نهاية جلسة المجموعة المركزة،
and as I was thanking the mothers for their time,
وكنت أشكر الأمهات على إعطائنا من وقتهن،
the elderly lady looked at me while pointing at the young girl,
قامت السيدة بالنظر إلي وهي تشير إلى الفتاة،
and said to me, "Can you help us with...?"
ومن ثم قالت لي "هل من الممكن أن تساعدينا...؟"
Not quite sure what she expected me to do,
ولم أكن أعرف ماذا كانت تتوقع مني أن أفعل،
I looked at the young girl and smiled,
فنظرت إلى الفتاة الصغيرة وابتسمت،
and in Arabic I said,
وقلت بالعربية،
"Salaam alaikum. Shu-ismak?"
"السلام عليكم. شو اسمك؟"
"What's your name?"
"ما هو اسمك؟"
She looked at me really confused and unengaged,
فنظرت إلي وهي مرتبكة ومشوشة،
but then said, "Halul."
لكن بعدها قالت هلول.
Halul is the pet's name for the Arabic female name, Hala,
وهلول هو اسم الدلع لإسم الأنثى هالة في العربية،
and is only really used to refer to really young girls.
ويستخدم فقط للإشارة للفتيات الصغيرات.
At that point I realized that actually Hala was probably much older than 13.
وفي هذه اللحظة أدركت أنه من المحتمل أن تكونهالة أكبر من 13 عامًا
It turns out Hala was a 25-year-old mother to three young children.
وأتضح أن عُمرَ هالة كان 25 عاماً وهي أم لثلاثة أطفال صغار.
Hala had been a confident, bright, bubbly, loving, caring mother
كانت هالة أمًا واثقة من نفسها حيوية ومهتمة ومحبة
to her children,
لأطفالها،
but the war had changed all of that.
لكن الحرب غيرت كل هذا.
She had lived through bombs being dropped in her town;
لقد عاشت قصف بلدتها بالقنابل؛
she had lived through explosions.
وعاشت حدوث الانفجارات.
When fighter jets were flying around their building,
عندما كانت الطائرات المقاتلة تحلق فوق مبناهم،
dropping bombs,
ملقيةً القنابلَ،
her children would be screaming, terrified from the noise.
كان أطفالها يصرخون خائفين من الضجة.
Hala would frantically grab pillows and cover her children's ears
وكانت هالة تقوم بإمساك الوسائد بشكل مسعور لتغطي آذان أطفالها
to block out the noise,
لتحجب الضجيج عنهم،
all the while screaming herself.
وكل هذا الأمر وهي تصرخ.
When they reached the refugee camp
وعندما وصلوا إلى مخيم اللاجئين
and she knew they were finally in some kind of safety,
وأيقنت أنها نوعاً ما أنها في مكان آمن،
she completely withdrew to acting like her old childhood self.
قامت بالانطواء على نفسها بشكل كامل متقمصةً دور طفولتها القديم.
She completely rejected her family --
ورفضت عائلتها تماماً
her children, her husband.
أطفالها وزوجها.
Hala simply could no longer cope.
لم تتمكن هالة من التأقلم مع الأمر.
This is a parenting struggle with a really tough ending,
وهذا صراع في التربية الوالدية بنهاية قاسية،
but sadly, it's not uncommon.
ولكن للأسف، هذا أمرٌ مألوف.
Those who experience armed conflict and displacement
الأشخاص الذين عاشوا صراعاً مسلحاً ونزوحاً.
will face serious emotional struggles.
سوف يواجهون صراعات عاطفية جِدية.
And that's something we can all relate to.
وهذا أمر يمكننا أن نحس به.
If you have been through a devastating time in your life,
إذا مررت بأوقات مدمرة في حياتك،
if you have lost someone or something you really care about,
أو إذا فقدت شخصاً أو شيئاً عزيزاً على قلبك،
how would you continue to cope?
كيف من ممكن أن تجاري هذا الأمر؟
Could you still be able to care for yourself and for your family?
هل من الممكن أن تبقى مهتماً بنفسك وبعائلتك؟
Given that the first years of a child's life are crucial
بما أن أول سنوات الحياة للطفل تعتبر مَصِيرِيّة
for healthy physical and emotional development,
لنموه الجسدي والعاطفي السليم.
and that 1.5 billion people are experiencing armed conflict --
ولأن 1.5 مليار شخص يعانون من صراع مسلح --
many of whom are now joining our communities --
والذي ينضم كثيرٌ منهم الآن لمجتمعاتنا --
we cannot afford to turn a blind eye
لا يمكننا غض البصرعنهم
to the needs of those who are experiencing war and displacement.
وعن احتياجات هؤلاء الذين تعرضوا للحرب والنزوح.
We must prioritize these families' needs --
لذلك يجب وضع احتياجات هذه العائلات كأولوية --
both those who are internally displaced, and those who are refugees worldwide.
سواء كانوا نازحين داخلياً أو لاجئين في جميع أنحاء العالم.
These needs must be prioritized by NGO workers, policy makers,
يجب وضع هذه الاحتياجات كأولوية من قبل عاملي المنظمات غير حكومية وصناع القرار.
the WHO, the UNHCR and every single one of us
ومنظمة الصحة العالمية ومن قبل مفوضية الأمم المتحدة لشؤون اللاجئين، وكل واحد منا
in whatever capacity it is that we function in our society.
مهما كانت حجم تأثيرنا داخل مجتمعنا.
When we begin to recognize the individual faces of the conflict,
عندما بدأنا بالتعرف على الأوجه الفردية للنزاع،
when we begin to notice those intricate emotions on their faces,
عندما بدأنا بملاحظة الانفعالات المعقدة على وجوهم،
we begin to see them as humans, too.
بدأنا نراهم على أنهم بشر، أيضًا.
We begin to see the needs of these families,
بدأنا نرى احتياجات هذه العائلات،
and these are the real human needs.
احتياجات إنسانية حقيقية.
When these family needs are prioritized,
عندما تصبح احتياجات هذه العائلات كأولوية،
interventions for children in humanitarian settings
ستوضع التدخلات من أجل الأطفال في الأوضاع الإنسانية
will prioritize and recognize the primary role of the family in supporting children.
كأولويات وسيتم التعرف على الدور الأساسي للعائلات في دعم الأطفال.
Family mental health will be shouting loud and clear
ستصرخ الصحة النفسية العائلية بشكل عال وواضح
in global, international agenda.
في العالم وفي الأجندات الدولية.
And children will be less likely to enter social service systems
وسيصبح أقل احتمالاً أن يدخل الأطفال نظم الخدمة الاجتماعية
in resettlement countries
في البلدان التي استوطنوها
because their families would have had support earlier on.
لأن عائلاتهم سوف تحصل على مساعدة في وقت مبكر.
And we will be more open-minded,
وسنكون أكثر تفهماً،
more welcoming, more caring
وأكثر ترحيباً وأكثر اهتماماً
and more trusting to those who are joining our communities.
وأكثر ثقة لهؤلاء الذين ينضمون إلى مجتمعاتنا.
We need to stop wars.
نحن بحاجة لإيقاف الحروب !
We need to build a world where children can dream of planes dropping gifts,
نحن بحاجة لبناء عالم يمكن للأطفال أن يحلموا فيه بطائرات ترمي الهدايا،
and not bombs.
لا القنابل.
Until we stop armed conflicts raging throughout the world,
حتى نوقف هيجان النزاعات المسلحة عبر العالم،
families will continue to be displaced,
ستستمر العائلات بالنزوح،
leaving children vulnerable.
وترك الأطفال مستضعفين.
But by improving parenting and caregiver support,
لكن بتحسين التربية الوالدية ودعم مقدمي الرعاية الصحية.
it may be possible to weaken the links between war and psychological difficulties
قد يكون من الممكن إضعاف العلاقة بين الحرب والعوائق النفسية
in children and their families.
عند الأطفال وعائلاتهم.
Thank you.
شكراً لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)